<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An homilie of Marye Magdalene declaring her ferue[n]t loue and zele towards Christ / written by that famous clerke Origene ; newly translated ...</title>
            <author>Origen.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1565</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08528</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2254</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23194796</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23194796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08528)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1800:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An homilie of Marye Magdalene declaring her ferue[n]t loue and zele towards Christ / written by that famous clerke Origene ; newly translated ...</title>
                  <author>Origen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[89] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Reginalde Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.LXV [1565]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An homilye of Abraham" has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸ F⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John XX --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis XXII --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:1"/>
                  <p>An Homilie of Marye Magda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lene, declaring her ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t loue and zele towards CHRIST: written by that famous clerke ORIGENE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly Tranſlated and Imprinted</hi> ANNO DOM. M.D.LXV</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Scriptural_citations">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:2"/>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Prouerbiorum. 1.</bibl>
                     <p>Audiens Sapiens, ſapientior erit.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Prouerb. 18.</bibl>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Non recipit Stultus verb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> prudentiae:</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Niſi ea dixeris quae verſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur in corde cius.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>This worthye man Origene lyued and taught in the yeare of our Lord, 225.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="homily">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:2"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>The Goſpel, Iohannis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0.</bibl>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ARY ſtoode without at the ſepulchre, wee pinge: And as ſhe wept, ſhe bowed herſelf into the Sepulchre.</p>
                        <p>And ſaw two Angels in white, ſitting, the one at the head, and the other at the fete, where the body of IES VS had layne.</p>
                        <p>And they ſaide vnto her: Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, why weepeſt thou? She ſayd vnto them: They haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away my lorde, &amp; I knowe not where they haue layd him.</p>
                        <p>When ſhe had thus ſaid, ſhe turned her ſelfe backe, and ſaw
<pb facs="tcp:26375:3"/>
IESVS ſtanding, and knewe not that it was IESVS.</p>
                        <p>Ieſus ſaieth vnto her: Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, why weepeſt thou? whom ſekeſt thou? She ſuppoſing that he had ben the gardyner, ſaide vnto him: Sir, if thou haſt born him hence, tell me where thou haſt laid him, &amp; I wil take him away. IESVS ſaide vnto her: Mary. She turned her ſelfe, and ſaid unto him: Raboni, whiche is to ſay, Maiſter.</p>
                        <p>IESVS ſaith vnto her: Touche me not, for I am not yet aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to my Father, but go to my breethern, and ſay vnto them: I aſcend vnto my father, and to youre father, and to my GOD, &amp; your GOD.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:3"/>
                  <head>Marye ſtoode without at the Sepulchre, wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>VRPOSING</hi> to ſpeak to your charytable ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſolemnitie, (moſt derely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) the godly loue of that bleſſed woman Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Magdalene recourſed to my remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, howe, for that ſhe loued our Lorde aboue all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, folowed hym goynge to his death, where his Diſciples for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoke him: And howe for that ſhe was kyndled with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire of true loue, in her vehement deſire we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge continually, departed not frome his ſepulcher. For Marye (as ſayeth the Euangeliſt) ſtode without at the Sepulcher weping. We
<pb facs="tcp:26375:4"/>
do hear (welbelo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d) of Maries ſtanding without at the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, we heare alſo how ſhe we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, let vs (if we can) conſyder the cauſe of her ſtandyng, let vs alſo ſe why ſhe wepeth: for both of this her ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding may we take profite, and alſo of her weeping may we be edifyed. Loue it was that made her to ſtand, &amp; ſorowe conſtrained her ſo to wepe. She ſtoode lookyng aboute, yf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance ſhe coulde ſee him whom ſhe loued. But wepte therfore, bicauſe whom ſhe ſought for, ſhe thought was quite taken away, wherby her ſorow was doubled: Fyrſte ſorowynge for hym being dead, and now ſorowing for him taken away: and of both griefes this laſte was the greater, for it was without comfort. The firſt cauſe of her ſorowynge was for
<pb facs="tcp:26375:4"/>
that ſhe had loſt his lyfe: but of this ſorowe had ſhee ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for that ſhe thought to haue retained hym dead as he was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But yet of this heauynes could ſhe not fynd comfort, for that ſhe found not his dead body. Thus fearing if that ſhe found not his body, the loue of him her May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wold ſone waxe colde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her breaſte, by the ſyghte yet whereof ſhee hoped ſhee mighte ware warme againe. In deede Mary was com to his ſepulchre bringing with her the odours &amp; ointmentes whiche ſhe had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, that as before when hee was alyue ſhee had annoynted with precious oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t his fete, ſo now ſhe mought anoynte his whole dead body with oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and wyth her ſpyces embaulme it. And lyke as fyrſte ſhe had at<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26375:5"/>
his feete ſhedd her teares and wept bitterly, and with her tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res watred his feet for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of her owne ſoule: ſo now ſhe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to water the Sepulcher with teares for the deathe of her Maiſter. But fyndinge not the bodye in the Sepulchre, her laboure of anointinge was loſt, but the ſorowe of her waylyng more increaſed. Preſent he was not to haue her ſeruice, and yet abſent he was not to cauſe her to ſorowe. Preſente he was not whome ſhe would haue embau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed, and yet abſent he was not to cauſe her to weepe. Therfore the more ſhe wepte, the further he was abſente. Certes Mary bitterly wept, for Sorowe was heaped vppon ſorowe. And two great ſorowes ſhe caried in one heart, whiche fayne ſhe woulde
<pb facs="tcp:26375:5"/>
haue eaſed with her teares, but they coulde not. And therefore was wholye plunged in ſorowe, fainting both in heart and body, and what ſhe ſhold do ſhe knew not: for what could this woman do but wepe? whiche bothe had dolor intolerable, and founde in comforte no remedy? In deede Peter and Iohn came with her to the Sepulcher, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they founde not the body, they wente foorthwith theyr waye home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>But Mary abode without at the Sepulcher weeping.</hi> And as one<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> hoping againſt hope, did yet pet ſouere in hope. Peter and Iohn were afrayd, and therfore ſtode not, but Mary feared not, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had nothinge lefte her (as ſhe thought) for whiche ſhee ought to feare, for ſhee had loſte her Maiſter, whome ſhee loued
<pb facs="tcp:26375:6"/>
ſo ſingularly, that beſide him ſhe could loue nothing, could hope for nothing: ſhe had loſte the life of her foule, &amp; nowe ſhe thought it better to dye than to liue, thin king perhappes in her death to haue founde, whome in her lyfe ſhe coulde not fynde, withoute whom notwithſtanding ſhe was not able to lyue. Strong as the<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.</note> Deathe is loue: for what more could death do in Marye? Shee became as it were without life, without ſence: hauing ſence ſhe vſed no ſence: Seinge, ſhe dyd not ſee: hearing, ſhee heard not, neither was ſhe where ſhe was, for wholy was ſhee there where her Maiſter was: who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge where he was, ſhee knewe not: ſhe ſoughte for him, but found him not, and therfore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding at the Tombe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:6"/>
and wept, altogether lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, all together miſerable. O Mary what hope, what cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail, what heart was in the, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone didſt ſtande at the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre when the Diſciples were departed? Thou cameſt before them, thou returnedſt with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and after them alſo there remai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nedſt. Why dyddſt thou thys? wert thou wiſer then they? Or didſt thou loue more then they, bycauſe thou fearedſte not as they? Truely Mary was nowe wiſe in nothyng but in louinge, and to ſorowe for her beloued. She had forgot to feare, forgot to ioy, yea forgot her owne ſelf. What ſhoulde I more ſay? She had forgote all thynges, except him whome ſhee loued aboue al things. And (which is wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful) ſhee was ſo forgetfull, that ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:26375:7"/>
knewe not him neither. Beleue me, if ſhe had knowen hym, ſhe had not ſearched for hym in his Tombe: and if ſhe had kept his words ſtill in minde, ſhe had not forowed as of one deade, but ſhould haue reioyced of him, as liuing: nor ſhould ſhe haue wept as of one which was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away but ſhe ſhould haue reioyced for that he was riſen again. For Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus had foreſpoken that thus he<note place="margin">Luce. 14.</note> ſhould dyc, and that he ſhoulde riſe againe the thirde day. But alack for pitie, ouermuch ſorow had filled her heart, &amp; had quite blotted out the remembraunce of theſe words. In her no ſence remained, al counſel in her was loſte, all hope failed: to weepe her belly full, did only remaine. She wepte therfore, for weepe ſhe might. <hi>She bowed down her ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:26375:7"/>
and looked into the Tombe, and ſawe two Angels ſitting in white, one at the ſee te, the other at the head, which ſayd vnto her: woman, why wepeſte thou?</hi> O Marye, loe, nowe thou haſte founde great comforte, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunce it hath happened vnto thee better then thou haſte ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: for thou ſoughteſt one, and haſt found two. Thou ſoughteſt one dead, and haſt found two li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Thou haſt found that ſeme to take care for thee, and that will eaſe thy heauineſſe. For he whom thou ſekeſt ſemeth to ſet nought by thy ſorowinge, he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to regarde thy teares. Thou calleſtc him, and he hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not: Thou prayeſt, and he geueth no fauorable care vnto thee. Thou ſekeſt him, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt him not: Thou knockeſte, but he openeth not. Thou folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſte
<pb facs="tcp:26375:8"/>
him, and he flyeth. Alas what meneth this? O lord what a greate chaunge is this? Alas how is al turned vpſide downe? For this is <hi>IESVS</hi> who of late went from the: and how co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth this thus to paſſe? Peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thou knoweſt not whether he loueth thee. Once he loued the, once he defended thee from<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> the Phariſey, once hee excuſed<note place="margin">Luc. 10.</note> the to thy ſiſter diligently, once hee commended thee as when thou annoyntedſt his feete with oyntmente, water edſt them with<note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note> thy teares, and wypedſt theym with thy heare, he aſſwaged thy ſorow, forgaue thy ſinnes. Once<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.</note> he ſought thee when thou werte not preſente, hee called for the when thou wert away, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the by thy ſiſter to come vnto hym, ſhee ſaynge: Thee
<pb facs="tcp:26375:8"/>
Maſter is here and calleth the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O howe quickly did Mary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ariſe after ſhe heard that, how carefullye came ſhee, and after her acuſtomed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner fel at thy fete? O ſweete <hi>IESV,</hi> thou whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſaweſt her weepe, weeptſt alſo. O how pitifully diddeſte thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte her when thou ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Where haue ye laid hym? To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, for the loue of her which muche loued thee, thou didſt raiſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death her brother Lazarus, and ſo thou turnedſt the mourning of this thy louer into ioye. And O moſte gentle Maſter, what hath this diſciple ſince offended the? And wherein hath this thy d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>relouer diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the kyndenes of thy heart, in that thou goeſt ſo from her? We haue ſince that time heard of no offence do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by her, except bicauſe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:9"/>
whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wert puried, <hi>She came in the morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and that very<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> early before all other to the Sepulchre,</hi> brynging ointeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes wherwith ſhe might an<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oynte thy body. And when ſhe<note place="margin">Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> found the not in the Sepulchre, ſhee ran and tolde this thing vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thy diſciples. They cam, they ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>we, and they ſtraighte wente theyre way againe: but ſhe ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſtil and wepeth. And if this be an offence, if all this be done for loue of the, and of a feruent deſire ſhe beareth towards the, wherfore goeſt thou thus from her? why doeſt thou thus hid thy ſelfe? thou that loueſte all that loue the, and thou that art fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſeke the: for thou ſayeſt: I loue thoſe that loue me.<note place="margin">Prou. 8.</note> Why doth not therfore this ſely woman finde the, whiche did ſo early watche for the? Why doſte
<pb facs="tcp:26375:9"/>
thou not comforte her teares whiche ſhe ſheddeth for the her lord, like as thou didſt once com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort her teares which ſhee ſhede for her brother? If truly thou louedſt her after thy wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, what meaneſt thou to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe her deſire? O true and faithfull Maiſter, call to thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce the good reporte and teſtymony thou once gaueſt of her to her ſyſter Martha. For thou ſaidſt: Mary hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the beſt part, which ſhall not be taken from her. In dede Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">Luc: 10.</note> did choſe the beſte parte, for ſhee did choſe to ſtande at thy fete and to heare thy preaching. She choſe in dede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt part, for The ſhe choſed. But how is this true <hi>which ſhall not be taken from her,</hi> yf thou bee taken from her? and if the beſte parte
<pb facs="tcp:26375:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26375:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26375:11"/>
that ſhe choſe bee not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, why then wepeth ſhe? Or what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ſhe ſeke? Certes Mary ſeketh nothinge els but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche ſhe choſe. And for this alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſhe ceaſeth not to wepe for that which ſhe hathe choſen ſhe hath now loſt. Therfore (O thou man ſauiour and keper) either ſaue in her the parte ſhee hathe choſen, or els I knowe not how this is true, <hi>which ſhall not bee taken from her,</hi> vnles yt maye be thus vnderſtanded, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou art taken from her ſighte, from her corporall eyes, yet arte thou not taken awaye from her heart. But alas Mary why makeſt thou any longer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riynge? why arte thou trobled? why wepeſt thou? Loe, ſee thou haſt Angels, let the ſight of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſuffice the. For paraduen
<pb facs="tcp:26375:11"/>
ture, he whome thou ſekeſt, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wepeſt, eſpieth in the ſomething for which he will not be ſene of the: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of now thy ſorow, meaſure thy teares: ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to mynde what he ſayd bothe to the and to other women: Wepe<note place="margin">Luc. 23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> not for mee. Therfore what is this thou doeſt? He forbad the to wepe, &amp; yet thou ſpareſte not to wepe. I feare me leaſt by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> weping y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offend him for whome thou doſte ſo continually wepe. For if he loued thy teares, hee could perchaunce no more now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he did once ſuffer thy teres. Now therfore heare my aduice. Let the comfortinge of Angels content and ſatiſfye the, abyde thou with them, aſke &amp; inquire of them. And it may fortune y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall tel what is become of him thou ſekeſt, and for whom
<pb facs="tcp:26375:12"/>
thou wepeſt. And I beleue aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redlye, theyr comminge was to be are witnes of him, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he whom thou wepeſt for, hath ſent them for himſelfe &amp; for thy ſelfe, to tell the of his Reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to comfort thy lamenting. <hi>For they ſaid to her: woman, why wepeſt thou?</hi> What is the cauſe of this thy great hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines? hyde not thy teares from vs, open to vs thy grief, and we ſhal ſhew the thy deſire. Marye waſted with to much ſorow out of meaſure, and as it were who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt in a traunce, receiueth no comforte, &amp; reſorteth to no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, but muſeth thus within her ſelfe and ſayth: Alas that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I was borne, what comfort is this? what manner of viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is this? All co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortes be but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> burthen vnto me, they do but
<pb facs="tcp:26375:12"/>
greue me, and not comforte me, For I ſeke the Creator, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heaui to my ſight is al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of creature. I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde Angels, with Angels will not I abyde, for they may aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente my ſorrowe, but they can not vtterly put away my ſorow. If they ſhall begin to tel me ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny things, and I to euery thing ſhal make them a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere, I feare me they will rather hinder my loue, then furder my loue. To be ſhorte, I ſeke not for Angels, but him who made me and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. I ſeke not angels, but the Lorde of my ſelf and of angels. They haue take away my ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lorde, him onely will I ſeeke, he alone can comfort me: but I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel where thei haue laid him. I looke about if I can ſee him, but I ſe him not: faine
<pb facs="tcp:26375:13"/>
I wolde finde the place where he is layed but I fynde it not. O wofull W<hi rend="sup">t</hi>oman that I am, what ſhall I do? whether ſhal I go? and whether is my beloued gon? I ſought for him in his Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulchre, and there I found him not. I called him, but he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me not: wo is me, where ſhal I ſeeke him? where ſhall I fynd him? I will riſe truly, I will go about, I will ſearch in al places I can, I will geue no ſleepe to myne eyes, I will geue no reſte to my feete, vntil I ſhall fynde him whome my Soule loueth. Wepe ye myne eyes, guſhe out with teares &amp; ſtynte not, walke ye my feete, runne about &amp; reſte not. Alas alas whether is my ioye gone? where doth my loue hyde him? where is my ſweete Lorde? why haſt thou m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> health
<pb facs="tcp:26375:13"/>
forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me? O vnſufferable ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes: O intolerable perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of minde, I ſe troble on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, &amp; what to chuſe I know not. If I abide next his Tomb, yet I finde him not. yf I go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Tombe, I know not wretch whether to go, I know not wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſeeke him. To departe from the Tombe is death vnto me, to ſtande at the Tombe is griefe incurable: how be it, better it is for me to keepe ſtill my Lordes Tombe, then to go far from it any further: for in goinge fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perchaunce at my returne again, I ſhall fynde bothe him take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, &amp; alſo his ſepulcher deſtroyed. I will ſtande there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; here will I dye. that yet at leſte wyſe I may be buried nye the ſepulchre of my Lorde. O how happy ſhal my body bee,
<pb facs="tcp:26375:14"/>
if it bee buried nighe vnto my Maſter. O how bleſſed ſhall my Soule be, whiche paſſing forth of thys bryckle veſſel of my bodie, may by and by enter into my Lords glorious Sepulcher. My body hath alwaies ben to my ſoule labour and trauaile, my Lords ſepulcher ſhallbe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me reſt and honor. Therfore I will not forſake this Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, bycauſe thus to die it ſhall be my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, and in my death it ſhall be my reſte. So longe as I liue I will abide by it, when I dye I wil cleaue faſt vnto it, neither aliue nor dead I wil be ſeperated from it. Alas what a wretched woman I am, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did I not then this foreſee when I behelde my lorde bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? why did not I ſtande with him? wherefore did I not with trewe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:14"/>
attendance keepe the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulchre: then had I not beway<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led his taking away, for I had either withſtanded them which toke him away, or els had gone after them. But O woful caſe, I wold haue kepte the lawe, and haue let go the Lord of the law: I wolde haue obeied the lawe, and haue not kept him to whom the lawe it ſelfe is obediente, though with Chriſte to abyde had not ben to tranſgreſſe the lawe, but to fulfyl the lawe. For the paſchal Lambe is not diſtei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by the deathe of him, but is again iterate &amp; renewed. His corps doth not defile the clea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, but clenſeth the defiled: he hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth all ſuche as touch him, and dothe illuminate all ſuche as come to him. But what do I re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>newe the memory of my ſorow?
<pb facs="tcp:26375:15"/>
I wente, I returned, I founde the Tombe opened, but founde not him I ſoughte for. I will ſtande therefore, I will waite, lokinge if happely hee may any where appeare. But howe, ſhall I ſtande alone deſolate? The Diſciples be gone theire waye, and haue left me alone weping. None do appeare who woulde ſorow with me. No where doth hee appeare, whiche with mee wolde ſeeke the Maiſter. Here haue appeared Angels, but I knowe not for what cauſe they haue appeared. If to comforte me, they oughte not then to bee ignorante wherefore I weepe. If they bee not ignorante for what I weepe, why ſay they to mee: Why wepeſt thou? Do they therefore queſtion with mee, to let me from wepinge? I beſeche
<pb facs="tcp:26375:15"/>
them, not to ſwade me to that, that they will not counſell mee to that, for or els let them kill me. What needes mo wordes? I will not obey them, I will not ceaſe to weepe duringe my lyfe but I finde my lorde. But what may I do to finde him? whither ſhall I turne me? to whom ſhall I go? of whome ſhal I inquire? of whome ſhall I aſke counſail? who ſhal haue compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on me? who ſhall comfort me? who ſhall<note place="margin">Cant. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſhew me whom my ſoul loueth,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> where he is beſtowed, where he lieth at noontide? where he reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth? I beſeche you tel him how I pyne with loue and conſume with ſorowe, and that there is no dolor as is my dolor. Turne<note place="margin">Tren. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> againe my beloued, turn again<note place="margin">Cant: 6.</note> my hartes deſire and dearling.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 50.</note> O amiable, O delitable, geue againe to me the gladnes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:26375:16"/>
comfortable preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Shew me<note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> thy countinaunce, let thy voice<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.</note> ſounde in mine eares, for thy<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0, 118.</note> voice is ſweete, and thy viſage is beutiful. O my hope, confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d mee not in myne expectation. Shew me thy face, and it ſhall ſuffice my ſoul. While Marye did thus mourn and thus wept as ſhe ſpak theſe things, <hi>She tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her ſelfe back, and ſawe Ieſus ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, and knew not it was Ieſus. Ieſus ſaid vnto her woman why wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt thou? &amp; Whome ſeekeſt thou?</hi> O thou the deſire of her ſoule, why doeſte thou aſke her <hi>why wepeſte thou? and whome ſeekeſte thou?</hi> She but a little before, with her very eies, to the great dolour of her heart, beheld the her whole hope, to be hanged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the tree, and ſaieſte thou nowe vnto her, why wepeſt thou? She the third
<pb facs="tcp:26375:16"/>
day beheld thy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des wherwith ſhe hath ben ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleſſed, thy feet which ſhe had kiſſed, and whiche ſhe had watered with her teares nailed vpon the croſſe, &amp; thou be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing her whole ſorow, ſaieſt vnto her: Why wepeſt thou? She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp of her ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, thy ſpirite: and ſaieſt thou now, why wepeſt thou? Yea fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermore ſhe ſuppoſeth thy body is ſtoln away whych ſhe came to anoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by ſom mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es ſhe might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte her ſelf, and ſaieſt thou, <hi>why wepeſt thou? whome ſeekeſt thou?</hi> Thou well knoweſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the alone ſhe ſeeketh, the alone ſhe loueth, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe contemneth all things, and ſayeſte thou, What ſeekeſte thou? Swete Maiſter, for what purpos I pray y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doeſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke this womans ſpirite? for what purpoſe doeſte thou vexe her Soule? She wholye depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:26375:17"/>
on thee: ſhe wholye aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in thee. All her hope is in the, all diſpaire in her ſelf. She doth ſo ſeeke the, that ſeekinge the, ſhe can ſeeke nothinge but the, ſhe can minde nothinge but the: and therefore perchaunte ſhe doth not know the, becauſe ſhe is not in her ſelfe, but for thy ſake is out of her ſelfe: why ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſaieſt thou: Why weepeſt thou? whome ſekeſt thou? Doeſt thou thinke that ſhe can ſay: I wepe for the, I ſeek the, except thou firſt inſpire her, and ſay in her heart: I am he whome thou we peſte for, and for whom thou ſekeſte? Doeſte thou thinke that ſhe can knowe the, ſo longe as it ſhal pleaſe the to hide thy ſelf? <hi>But ſhe ſuppoſinge that he had ben the gardiner, ſaid vnto him: Sir, if thou haſt caried him hence, tell me where thou
<pb facs="tcp:26375:17"/>
haſt laid him, and I will take him</hi> vp. O ſorowe miſerable, O loue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpeakable. This woman was ſo couered with a thicke cloude of wo and ſorowe, that ſhe ſaw not the Sun, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the morning tyde ariſing, ſhone by her windowes, and by the eares of her bodye was now entred into the houſe of her heart. But bicauſe ſhe la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in her loue, of this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhinge the eyes of her heart became ſo dym, that ſhe coulde not ſe him whome ſhe ſawe. For ſhe did ſee Ieſus, but ſhe knew not it was Ieſus. O Mary, it thou ſekeſt Ieſus, why doeſte thou not acknowledge Ieſus? And if thou knoweſt Ieſus, why ſekeſt thou Ieſus? Beholde, Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus commeth vnto the, and hee whom thou ſekeſt aſketh of the? Woman, why wepeſt thou? and
<pb facs="tcp:26375:18"/>
thou ſuppoſeſt him to be a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>er, to ſhew thou knoweſt him not. For Ieſus is alſo a gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, becauſe he ſoweth all good ſeede in the gardin of thy ſoule, and in the hearts of his faithful he planteth euery good Herbe, and watereth it in the ſoules of his ſainctes. And it is <hi>IESVS</hi> himſelf which talketh with the. But therefore perhaps thou do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt not knowe him, bycauſe hee corporally talketh with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Thou ſekeſt a dead one, and therefore thou doeſt not acknowledg him as liuing. Haue I not truly eſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that this is the cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he went from the? and why he appeared not vnto the? For why ſhould he appeare vnto the for whome thou doeſt not ſeke? Thou verely ſoughteſt for that which was not, and ſoughteſt
<pb facs="tcp:26375:18"/>
not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which was. Thou didſt ſeke Ieſus, and didſte not ſeke Ieſus: and therefore in ſeinge Ieſus, thou didſt not knowe Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus. O pittiful and ſweete Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I can not altogether excuſe this thy diſciple: I can not frely defende this her error: And yet for all that ſhee erred, bycauſe ſhe ſoughte the for ſuche an one as once ſhe had ſeene the, and for ſuche a one as ſhe had lefte the, when thou wert laied in thy graue. For ſhe had ſene thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taken downe dead from the croſſe, &amp; layed in a tombe, and ſo greate ſorowe had taken hold of her for thy death, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe coulde not hope of thy life. And ſuche ſorowe had poſſeſſed her herte for thy buriall, that ſhee coulde thinke nothinge of thy reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, To conclude, Ioſeph
<pb facs="tcp:26375:19"/>
put thy body into a tombe, &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry had buried there her ſpirite alſo, &amp; ſo vnſeparably ioyned it, &amp; as it were, vnited it with thy body, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe could more eaſily ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate her liuing ſoule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing body, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her louing ſpirit from thy dead body: for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of Mary was rather in thy body, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in her owne body. and when ſhe eaftſones ſoughte for thy body, ſhe did then alſo ſeeke for her own ſpirit: and when ſhe loſt thy body, ſhe loſt with it her own ſpirit: what meruaile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if ſhe had no ſenſe, which had loſt her ſpirit? what maruail was it if ſhe knew not the which had no ſpirite where with ſhee ſhoulde knowe the? Reſtore therfore vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to her again her ſoule, which thy body hath within it ſelfe, and ſhee ſhall recouer furthwith her ſenſe againe, and forſake her er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror
<pb facs="tcp:26375:19"/>
But how did ſhe erre which did ſo ſorowe for the, and did ſo loue the? Truly if ſhe erred, I ſpeake without doubtinge, that ſhe wyſt not ſhe erred, and ſo her error proceded not of error, but of loue and grefe. Therfore O mercifull and iuſte Iudge, the loue ſhee bare to thee, and the ſorowe ſhe toke for the, may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe her before the, if perhaps ſhe erreth of the. And marke not the error of the woman, but the loue of thy diſciple, whiche did not wepe of error but of ſorowe and of loue, and ſaid vnto the: Sir, if thou haſt borne him he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, tel me where thou haſt laid him, and I will take him vp. O how ſkilfully is ſhe ignorante, &amp; how learnedly doth ſhe erre? To the Angels ſhe ſaid, They haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him away, and they haue layed:
<pb facs="tcp:26375:20"/>
And ſhe ſaid not? Ye haue taken him, and Ye haue layed him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the angels neyther tooke the out of thy Tombe, nor layed the in any place: but to thee ſhee ſaid <hi>(If thou haſt borne him away)</hi> &amp;, <hi>(where haſte thou laied him)</hi> bicauſe thou indede didſt beare thy ſelfe out of the Tombe, and laydſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thy ſelf in the place where thou arte. To the angels ſhe ſaid not Tell ye me. bicauſe thee Angels coulde not tell wholy what had ben done of the, nor howe it had bene done of the, but to the ſhee ſaith: Tel thou me, bycauſe it is not vnpoſſible for the to tel that which was poſſible for the to do: for thou roſeſt againe by thyne owne power, &amp; that whiche was done of the, thou diddeſte it thy ſelfe. But what is this (Lorde) that Mary ſo often ſpeaketh &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26375:20"/>
repeteth this worde, Where haſte thou layd him? For ſhee had ſaid to the Apoſtles firſte of all, <hi>where haue they layed him?</hi> The ſelfſame anſwer ſhe ſpake vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angels, Wher haue they layed him? And nowe ſpeaketh to the of thy ſelfe, Where haſte thou layd him? This word wax eth exceding ſwete in her heart that ſo abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in her mouth. Lertes thy ſwetenes maketh it more ſweete, and ſhe dothe this for thy loue ſake, bycauſe ſhee reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth that thou ſaidſt once<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.</note> of her brother, Where haue ye laid him? for ſithens y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe heard this word of thy mouth, ſhe hath kept it diligently in her heart, and hath delighted to vſe it in her ſpeache. O howe dothe ſhee loue thy perſon, that ſo loueth thy voice? O how moch doth ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:21"/>
deſire to ſee thy countinaunce which ſo deſirouſly pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth thy worde? And howe gladlye wolde ſhe kiſſe thy feete, whiche ſo gladly vſeth thy ſayinges? what is this alſo (O good Ieſu) that ſhe ſpeaketh to the of the? <hi>And I will take him vp.</hi> Ioſeph feared and durſte not take doun thy body from the Croſſe but in the night, and but aſkinge it of Pilate: but Mary abydeth not<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.</note> for the night, nor fereth Pilate, but boldly pronounceth ſaying, <hi>I will take him vp.</hi> O Mary putte the caſe that the body of Ieſus were layed in the palayce of the high Preiſt where the cheife A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle did warme him ſelfe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyer, what woldeſte thow doe? <hi>I wolde take him vp.</hi> O wonderful woman in boldenes. O woman, no woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and what if the Dam
<pb facs="tcp:26375:21"/>
ſell, the dore keeper ſhould aſk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the? what wilt thou do? <hi>I wil take him vp.</hi> O vnſpeakable loue of this woman. O meruailous au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacitye of a woman. O woman, no woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſhe excepter hno place ſhe preferreth none, ſhe ſpeketh without fear, ſhe promiſeth abſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lutely, <hi>Tel me where thou haſte laied him, and I will take him vp.</hi> O Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man greate is thy faith, great is thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy. Therfore (O good Lorde) why haſte thou forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay: Let it be don vnto the as<note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> thou wilt? And, Be of good cher,<note place="margin">Mat. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> thy faith hath made y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſafe. Haſt<note place="margin">Pſal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 76.</note> thou forgotten to haue mercye? wherfore then doeſt thou not te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her where thou haſte layed thy ſelfe, that ſhe may take the vpp vpon her hert, and beare thee in her body, and ſhew the vnto thy diſciples. Do not (I beſeech the
<pb facs="tcp:26375:22"/>
ſweete Maiſter) prolonge her deſire any more: for lo now theſe three daies ſhee hathe endured waytinge for the, &amp; hath nothing<note place="margin">Mat. 8.</note> to eate, and hath naught where with to feede her hungry ſowle: but thou by diſcloſinge thy ſelfe, doeſt reache vnto her y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of thy body, &amp; doeſt fyl her with thy fragments of the baſket of her heart. Wherefore, if thou wilte that ſhe faynte not by the way, refreſſhe and comforte the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels of her ſoule with the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of thy taſte. For thou art<note place="margin">Sapi. 16.</note> the liuing bread whiche haſte in the al maner delectablenes and all ſauour of ſwetenes: for the life of her body will not long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, onles y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> quickly ſheweſt thy ſelf, which art the life of her ſoul. <hi>Ieſus ſayed vnto her: Mary. She turned her ſelfe and ſayd vnto him. Rabboni, which is to ſay: maiſter, Ieſus ſaied vn
<pb facs="tcp:26375:22"/>
to her. Touch me not.</hi> Opermutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the right hand of the higheſt. Greate ſorow is now turned in to greate ioy. The teares of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row be changed into the teares of loue. So ſone as Mary heard this worde, Marye, (for ſo was her Maiſter wonte to call her) ſhe did perceaue before in that name, a certain ſingular ſwete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of callinge, and by that ſhee knew him to be her Maiſter, of whom ſhe was called. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſpirite reuiued, &amp; her ſence came again. And when Ieſus wolde more haue added, Mary coulde not paciently tarry to heare any more: but for very greate ioye interrupted him, ſaying: Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boni. for ſhe thought ſhe needed no word that had found y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, and thought it farre more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to handel the word then
<pb facs="tcp:26375:23"/>
to hear any manner of wordes. O loue ſtronge and vnpacient. It was not enough for her to ſe Ieſus, and to ſpeake with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,<note place="margin">Luc. 6. and. 8.</note> onles alſo ſhe touched Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for ſhe knewe that vertue wente out from him, and howe that he healed all men. O moſte pitifull Lorde, and moſte ſwete Maiſter, how good arte thou to thoſe that be of a pure hearte:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 73.</note> howe ſweete art thou to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be of an vprighte hearte, and be<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ap. 1.</note> lowly in ſpirite. O howe bleſſed be they that ſeeke the in ſingel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of heart: and how happy be they that truſte in the. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily trew, &amp; vndoubtedly trewe, that thou loueſt althat loue the,<note place="margin">Prou. 8.</note> and doſte neuer forſake them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 9.</note> put their truſte in thee. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, this thy louer did ſeke the vnfainedly, and hath found the
<pb facs="tcp:26375:23"/>
trewly. She truſted in the, &amp; ſhe is not forſaken of the, but hath obteined by the, more then ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked for at the. Let vs therefore (bretherne) follow the good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thys woman, that we may come to the like effecte. Let eueri one wepe vnto Ieſus, and ſeeke faithfully Ieſus, that will not hyde hym ſelfe from a ſinner that ſeketh him. Learne ſinfull man of a ſinfull woman, whoſe ſinnes notwithſtandinge be forgeuen her: Learn to wepe for Gods abſence, and to deſire his preſence. Learne of Marye to loue Ieſus, and to truſt in Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus, and by ſeekinge Ieſus in this ſearch, to feare no aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and beſides Ieſus to receiue no comfort, and for Ieſus to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all thinges. Learn of Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to ſeeke for Ieſus in the Se
<pb facs="tcp:26375:24"/>
pulcher of thy heart, Rol away the ſtone from the doore of the Sepulcher of God, remoue all hardneſſe, and put away euerye thing that may hinder thy faith: take away all wordly deſire fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy hearte, and ſerche diligently whether Ieſus be in it. And if thou finde not Ieſus in it, ſtand without and weepe: perſiſte in faith, and looke outwardly to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whether happely y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> maieſt ſee hym in anye. And wythe weepinge pray Ieſus that hee wil vouchſafe to entre into the, and will dwell in the, and leſte perchance with a proud ſtiffe vp right necke, thou put him away from the: humbly incline thy ſelf and bowe downe vnto him, and looke often into the Sepulchre of God whiche is in thee, and if thou ſhalte ſee Angels there ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge,
<pb facs="tcp:26375:24"/>
one at the head, an other at the feete, that is, yf thou ſhalte knowe in thy hearte as it were heauenly deſires, appertaining aſwell to this actiue lyfe as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contemplatiue lyfe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which neuertheles thou canſt not ſee and haue Ieſus, bee not with theſe contentid, do not yet faint and geue ouer, but wepe &amp; ſeeke ſtill Ieſus in thy ſelf, vntil thou fynde him. And if he ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at any time to appeare vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, and to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him ſelf vnto thi deſire. doe not preſume of thy ſelfe as though thou knoweſt him, but inquire of him, and beſeche him he will ſhew him ſelfe vnto the. I dare boldely vndertake, if in faith thou ſhalte ſtande at the tombe of thy hearte, if wepingly y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſeeke Ieſus, &amp; ſhalt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſeki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhal bow down
<pb facs="tcp:26375:25"/>
thyſelfe with humbl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes, if by Maries exaumple thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of Ieſus, except y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> receueſt Ieſus, hee wil reuele him ſelfe vnto the, &amp; thou ſhalte fynde him and knowe him. So that thou ſhalt not neede to aſk of other, where is Ieſus, but thou ſhalte rather tel and ſhew him to others, &amp; ſay: For I haue ſeene the Lorde, and hee ſpake theſe things vnto me. To whom with the Father and the holye ghoſte bee all honor and glory, worlde without ende.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AN HOMILIE OF ABRAHAM,</hi> how he offered by his ſonne Iſaac. written by ORIGEN.</p>
                  <p>Newly tranſlated.</p>
                  <p>Anno. M.D.LXV.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="homily">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:26"/>
                  <head>An Homilie of Abraham, how he offered vp his Son: written by ORIGEN.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, God did proue Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and ſayd vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Take thyne onelye ſonne Iſaac whome thou loueſt, and offer him vp for a brent ſacrifice vn to me, in one of thoſe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines whiche I ſhall ſhew the.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26375:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>eue eare to this which I haue to ſay (I ſpeake to you y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> drawnye to the Lord) you I ſay which thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke your ſcluesto be faithfull, and conſider di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of the faith full is proued: as by the wordes which haue ben rehearſed vnto you, ſhall appeare. <hi>And it came to paſſe, that after theſe things almightye God did proue Abraham, and ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: Abraham, Abraham: and then anſwered he, Lo here I am.</hi> Marke wel euery thing as it is written: for in euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if a man can dig depe, he ſhal finde trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. and perhaps where it is not thought, ſhalbe hidden ſome precious Iewels of ſecret miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. This godly man is called
<pb facs="tcp:26375:27"/>
Abraham: &amp; no where we reade that God called him with that name, or that he ſpake to him ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, Abraham Abraham: for hee coulde not bee called of God by a name which ſhoulde be dimini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed, but he called him with that name whiche himſelfe did giue him: &amp; not with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name only he called him, but he dubleth his name, Abraham, Abraham. And when he had anſwered, Lo here I am, he ſayed vnto him: <hi>Take now thyne onelie ſonne whome thou loueſt, Iſaac I ſay, and offer thou him vp for a brent ſacrifice, in one of the montaines, which I will ſhew vnto the.</hi> For what cauſe God gaue him a name, and called him Abraham, himſelf declareth it, for (ſaithe he) I haue apoited the to be the father of many nations. This promiſe made God to him after
<pb facs="tcp:26375:27"/>
he had Iſmahell his ſonne: how be it he made the promiſe to be fulfilled in that ſone which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſhould be are vnto him. Thus therefore had hee kyndled hys hearte in the loue of his ſonne, not onely in conſideration of the poſterity, but alſo in the hope of the promiſes. And yet is he commaunded to offer this his ſonne to the Lorde for a bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Sacrifice in one of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines: his onlye Son in whom ſo great and maruelous promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were made: I ſay euen that ſonne, in whoſe reſpecte hee had his name to be called Abraham. What ſaiſt thou to this Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? what manner cogitations are toſſed in thy hearte? A worde is come from God him ſelf, which will diſcuſſe and trie thy faithe: What ſayeſt thou to this? What
<pb facs="tcp:26375:28"/>
thinkeſt thou? what muſeſt thou? doeſt thou thinke thus with thy ſelf, withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy heart: that if in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> promiſe is made vnto me, and I offer him vp for a brente ſacrifice, it muſte nedes fall out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe is fruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat? or rather doeſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thus rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within thy ſelf, &amp; ſaiſt: bicauſe it is not poſſible for him to lye who hath made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſe, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore what ſo euer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> promiſe be, it ſhal ſtand? How be it, becauſe I am ſo baſe, I am not hable to ſearche out the cogitations of ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a patriark, nor yet am I able to fynde out what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of deliberations that voice which came from God to proue him ſtirred him to, what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile it broughte with it, when he was commaunded to cal his onlie ſonne. Notwithſtandinge becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit which is in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phettes
<pb facs="tcp:26375:28"/>
ys ſubiect to prophettes,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> Paule the Apoſtle which (as I beleue) was inſtructed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpirite, what mynde, what counſail Abraham bare in his heart, hath reueled it ſayinge: Abraham in his faith ſtaggered not when he was about to offer vp his only ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, in whom he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes: iudgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thus in himſelfe: God was able to raiſe him vp again, thoughe he we are dead. Thus therefore doth the Apoſtle declare vnto vs the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations of this faithfull man, that the faith of the Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was then ſene to haue a be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning in Iſaac. Abraham ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did hope that his ſon Iſaac ſhould riſe agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And he beleued that it wolde be hereafter full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled which as yet was not don. How the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? be they Abrahams chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren which do not beleue to be
<pb facs="tcp:26375:29"/>
fulfilled in Chriſt, which he bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued wold be fulfilled in Iſaac? yea if I ſhould ſpeake yet more plainly: Abraham knew that he did forme out before as it were an Image of that truthe which was to follow: That is, he knew before that Chriſte ſhoulde bee borne of his ſeed, whiche ſhould as a more parfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct ſacrifice bee offred vp for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world: and that hee ſhoulde alſo riſe againe from deathe. But thus in the meane whyle (writeth Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) God did proue Abraham, and ſaid vnto him: <hi>Take vp thy on lye beloued ſonne whom thou derelye loueſt.</hi> It was not enough to ſay: Take vp thy ſon, but thi onli be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued ſonne. Let it be ſo, what is more added? <hi>And whome thou loueſt.</hi> O ſee &amp; conſider y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty grauity of this tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how
<pb facs="tcp:26375:29"/>
with ſo deare &amp; ſweete names, ſo oft and oft repeted, is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers heart and affecrio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſturred vp: whereby the freſhe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of his loue, this father ſhoulde holde of his righthande to offer vp his ſon: wherby the whole power of his fleſh ſhoulde fight againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of his heart. And further is added euen in the very rune when he proued him: <hi>Take vp (ſaith he) thy moſte deere Son Iſaac, I ſay, whome thou loueſt.</hi> Let it ſo he O Lorde, that thou putteſt the father in remembraunce of hys ſonne, and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt him to kill him, why addeſt thou, <hi>Thy moſt deere Son?</hi> Let this ſuffice to the torment of a Father, Thou ioynedſt to it again, <hi>Yea whom thou loueſt.</hi> Let this doble &amp; tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affliction be enough and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe to the Fathers hearte.
<pb facs="tcp:26375:30"/>
What need it to rehearſe to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory the name Iſaac: was not Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aduiſed of this, that his o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſo wel beloued ſon, he whom he loued, was called Iſaac. But why is mention made of him at this very time: was it for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham calling to his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce how thou ſaidſt vnto him, that in Iſaac thy ſede ſhalbe called, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in Iſaac ſhoulde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſes be fulfilled: and by rememberau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his name he ſhoulde be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſpaire of all the promiſes which wer made vnto him u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der that name? But what? All theſe thinges thus wer don, for that God did proue Abraham. And what yet foloweth? <hi>Go thy way, ſaith he, into the hie la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, to one of the mountaines which I wil ſhew the, and there offer thou him for a brent ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> Conſider euery thinge by it
<pb facs="tcp:26375:30"/>
ſelf, how the tentations aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>Get the vp into the hye lande.</hi> I pray you wolde not Abraham firſte be led with the childe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high land, &amp; to be placed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hill whiche the lorde had choſen out, &amp; there to be ſaid vnto him that he ſhoulde offer his ſonne? But it is firſte ſaid vnto him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde offer his ſonne, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is hee commaunded to goe to a highe Land, and to aſcende vp into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hill. What meaneth this? Truly, that whileſt he went and made his iournye, hee ſhoulde as I might ſay, be torn in peces by his owne thoughts through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the wholl way: and that hee ſhoulde be crucified of one ſide through the commaundemente of god vrging him, on the other ſide through the Fatherly affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his onely ſonne,g repining
<pb facs="tcp:26375:31"/>
and abhorring the facte. There<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, for this cauſe he was enioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to go a longe wave, to clyme vp an hye hill, to this inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that his fanſy and fayth, the loue of God, and the loue of his owne fleſh, the deſire of thinges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and the lookinge after thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges to come, ſhould ſtryue toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a time in all thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, he is ſent therfore into an hye lande. And it ſufficed not to preſcribe vnto the Patriarche whiche ſhoulde doe ſo not able a worke vnto the Lorde, for to go vnto an hye lande, but alſo he is commaunded to aſcend vp into an hye hill: Truly that he might forſake earthly things being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted by faith, &amp; aſcend to thoſe things which are aboue in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Ahraham then roſe earlye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, he ſadled his Aſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:26375:31"/>
and cut wood for to burne at the ſacrifice: hee toke his ſon Iſaac with him and two ſeruauntes, and came at the third day to the place that God apointed him to go vnto. <hi>Abraham roſe early.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore doth the text adde, Early in the morninge? paraduenture it wolde declare that light began to ſhine in his heart. He ſadleth his Aſſe, he prepareth wood, hee taketh vp his ſonne, he taketh no deliberation in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no ſtickinge or ſtaying, hee maketh no man priuy of his pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pos, but furth with he taketh him ſelfe to his Iourney, and came (as the texte ſaith) to the place which the Lorde tolde him of, on the third day. I here paſſe ouer to ſay what ſecret miſterye the thirde day doth ſignify, I onlye haue a regarde to the wiſdome
<pb facs="tcp:26375:32"/>
and purpoſe of God that min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to proue and try him. Was there no hill at al nigh at hand, ſeing the whole country was ſet in hilles, but that his Iournye muſte be drawne out three daie longe, and for the ſpace of thoſe three daies, his fathers heart muſt be tormented with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cares recourſinge together? ſo that all this longe tyme the father ſhould behold his ſonne, he ſhould eate meate with him, and ſo manye nightes the ſonne ſhoulde be embraced of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould ſitte in his fathers lap, and lie in his boſome? Se I pray you, how greatly his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions wer multipled &amp; encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. But yet the third day is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry apt to expreſſe miſteries: For when the people of Iſrael came out of Egipt, they did offer ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice
<pb facs="tcp:26375:32"/>
vnto god on the thirde day, and on the third day wer purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and Chriſtes reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was vpon the third daie: and manye other miſteries bec comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the thirde day. Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham (ſaith the texte) looked vp &amp; ſaw a far of the place apointed, &amp; he ſaid to his ſeruants: Staye ye here with the aſſe, <hi>I &amp; the child will go together to yender place, and when wee haue don our offering, we wil returne vnto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you againe.</hi> And thus he leaueth his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: for the ſeruants might not aſcende with Abraham vnto the place of ſacrifice which god had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. Therfore ſaith he to his ſeruants: <hi>Syt ye here, I &amp; the child will go vp into the hill, &amp; when we haue made our ſacrifice, wee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto you.</hi> Abraham I pray the tell me, doeſte thou ſay the
<pb facs="tcp:26375:33"/>
truth to thy ſeruants, that thou mindeſt to do ſacrifice &amp; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with thy child again vnto them, or doeſte thou diſſemble? If thou ſayeſt the truthe, ergo thou ſhalt not make him a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. If thou doeſt diſſemble, it becommeth not ſo greate a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch to diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble. What mind therfore doth this word bewray in th? Truth ſaith he I ſpeake, and I offer the child for a burnt ſacrifice: for to that intente do I carrye wood with me, &amp; with him will I returne vnto you. For I do beleue and this is my faith, that God is hable to raiſe hym vp, yea though he be dead. After this (ſaith the text) Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toke wood to the ſacrifice, and layd it vpon Iſaac his ſon: and he toke fier in his handes and a ſworde, and went for ward toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:26375:33"/>
In that Iſaac caried for him ſelfe wood vnto ſacrifice, it was a figure of that that Chriſt him ſelfe bare his owne croſſe. And yet to carry wood to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſts office. Thus is he made both Sacrifice &amp; Prieſt. But where as it is added in the text: They we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t both together, is referred vnto this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration: for when Abraham (as minding to make a ſacrifice) carried fyre and a knife, Iſaac doth not drag after him, but goeth iointly with him, to ſignifye that hee iointlye with him e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioined the preiſthod. And what followeth after this? Iſaac, ſaith the text, ſpake to his father Abraham: Father. euen this word ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at that time of his ſonne, was a word of muche tentario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For how thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke you? did the ſonne whiche was ſtraight
<pb facs="tcp:26375:34"/>
way to be ſacrificed, ſhake his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers bowels by this word? And although that Abraham was ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the more conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſet for the faithe that was in him, yet he putteth out a worde of lyke affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwered: What me neſt thou my ſonne? Whereunto he ſaid: Beholde (ſaith he) fyre &amp; wood, but where is the ſheepe to ſacrifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e? To theſe anſwered Abraham: O my ſonne, God wil prouide for him ſelfe a ſheepe to ſacrifice. Certenly this precyſe and ware anſwere of Abraham moueth me muche: for I can not tell what he ſaw in ſpirite, for that hee aunſwered not of the tyme preſent, but of the time to come: God himſelf will prouide a ſhepe for his ſacrifice. He aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with a Shal to his ſonne which aſked of him a thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb facs="tcp:26375:34"/>
For in dede the Lord him ſelf prouided to him ſelf a ſhepe in Chriſt, for that wiſdom it ſelf hath bulded to him ſelf his hous and he him ſelf hath humbled hym ſelf eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death: And what ſoeuer els y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> readeſte of Chriſte, thou ſhalt finde them donne, not by any neceſſity, but by free election. <hi>Then they both went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde together, and were come to the place which God did ſhew him.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Moiſes was come to the place which God did ſhewe vnto him, he is not permitted to clyme vp to it, before it was ſayde to him, <hi>Vnloſe the latchettes of thy ſhooes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy fete.</hi> But to Abraham no ſuch matter is ſayde nor to Iſaac, But thei clime vptogether, and put of no ſhowes. The reaſon peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture therof, was bicauſe Moiſes (how great ſoeuer hee
<pb facs="tcp:26375:35"/>
was) yet was he come out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, and therefore had his fete ſnared with ſome ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alitye. But Abraham &amp; Iſaac hadde no ſuche matter, but they came to the place, they builded the Alter, Abraham laid wood vpon the Altar, and bindeth the childe, he prepareth him ſelf to ſlea him. Many of you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heare theſe thinges in the Churche of God, are Fathers youre ſelues: And which of you thinkeſt thou, by hearinge this hiſtorye tolde, hath attained to ſuch conſtancy and ſtrength of minde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if your ſon, yea your o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſon, your derly beloued ſon perhaps be taken a way by death (both common and dew vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) frameth to him ſelfe Abraham for a patron, and laieth his ſtoutnes before youre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yes? yet truly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like ſtout mind
<pb facs="tcp:26375:35"/>
is not required of thee, that thou thy ſelfe bynd thy Son, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou thy ſelfe make him faſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou thy ſelfe prepare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword, that thou thy ſelfe ſhoulde ſlaye thine onely childe: (all theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries are not required at thy hand) but at the leaſt be conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in thy purpoſe and will, ſtedfaſt in faith, and cherefully offer thy Son to God: be a prieſt touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſoule of thy ſon. And it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not a prieſte that offereth ſacrifice to God, for to do it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingly.</p>
                  <p>Wilt thou vnderſtande that this is required of thee? Oure Lorde ſaith in the goſpel: If ye<note place="margin">Ihon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> were the children of Abraham, ye wolde truly do the workes of Abraham. Lo this is a woorke of Abraham: do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes which
<pb facs="tcp:26375:36"/>
Abraham did, but not with grief<note place="margin">2. Cor. 9.</note> and ſorrowe: For God loueth a chereful geuer. And if ye ſhal be thus readdy, it ſhal be ſaied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you of God: Clyme vp vnto this hygh Land, and to the hill which I will ſhew thee, &amp; there offerre vnto me thy ſon. And of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy ſon not in the deepe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the earth, nor in the vale of wepinge, but in the great and high hilles. Declare thou then, that faith in the Lorde is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then any carnal affection.</p>
                  <p>For Abraham (ſaith he) loued I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac his ſon, but he preferred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of God to his owne fleſhly loue: And ſo he was found not in the bowels of hys fleſhe, but in the bowels of Chriſte, that is in the bowels of the word of God, of truth and wiſedome.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham (ſaith the text) ſtretched
<pb facs="tcp:26375:36"/>
forth his hand to take the ſworde, and kill his Sonne. And the Angel of the lord called vnto him from heauen, &amp; ſaid: Abraham, Abraham And he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: Here I am, And he ſaid: Lay not thy hand vpon the childe, neither do any hurt to him. For now I know that thou feareſt God.</hi> It is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly out of this place obiected vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs, how god ſaith that he kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weth that Abraham did feare him, as if he had bene ignorante there of before. Wel, god which in dede knoweth all thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be done, did alſo know this thinge, and was not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt of it: but it is thus writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy cauſe, for thou haſte a faith in God, and yet excepte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> accompliſh the workes of faith, except thou obey, yea all the har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt commaundements, excepte thou offer vp ſacrifice, and ſhew plainelye that thou doeſt not ſet
<pb facs="tcp:26375:37"/>
more by father, mother, and chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by God, it ſhal not be ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>knoleged that thou feareſt God, neither ſhall it bee ſaid of thee: F or now I knowe that thou fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt God.</p>
                  <p>And beſides this, wee may here conſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Angel which is ſaid here to ſpeake theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to Abraham: in proceſſe afterwarde is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſhewed to be the Lord. Wherevppon I thinke thus: that as amonge vs men, he was found in his behaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour as man, ſo among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> he was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our as an Angel. And ſo the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen following his ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aumple, are glad of one Sinner which repentith, &amp; reioice great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, when men go forward in god lines.</p>
                  <p>For theſe Angels haue as it
<pb facs="tcp:26375:37"/>
were the ouerſighte of oure ſoules, vnto whom as tutors &amp;<note place="margin">Gal. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> gouernours, wee whiles we are yonglinges are committed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the time appointed by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be comme. Therefore thei ſay now concerninge the goinge forward in godlines of euery on of vs, that now I knowe that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> feareſt the Lord. But for a plai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner exaumple hereof: Be it ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I purpoſe in my minde to ſuffer martirdom, yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> angel can not ſave vnto mee, that nowe I knowe that thou feareſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord? for God only knoweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecret of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind. but if I abide torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts if I boldly publiſh a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if I conſtantly beare what ſoeuer ſhallbe doone vnto mee, then the Angell as comfortinge &amp; confirming me, may ſay: Now I knowe that thou feareſte the
<pb facs="tcp:26375:38"/>
Lorde.</p>
                  <p>Thus the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe thinges were ſpoken to Abraham, and hee ſo was pronounced to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. And why? Becauſe he ſpared not his owne ſonne. But let vs com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare theſe thinges with the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of the Apoſtle, where he ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> of god: which ſpared not his owne ſon, but did giue him for vs all. Beholde here howe God contendeth with men in bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liberalitie. Abraham offred to god his mortall ſonn not yet like to dye: God gaue his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mort all ſon for al men to death. What ſhall we ſay to theis thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges? What ſhall we render to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, for all that he hath beſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon vs? God the Father hath not ſpared his owne ſonne for vs. And which of you al (thin keſt thou) at any time ſhall hear
<pb facs="tcp:26375:38"/>
this voice of the Angel ſayinge vnto you: Now I know that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> feareſt God, bicauſe thou haſte not ſpared thy ſon, thy daughter thy wife: or thou haſt not ſpared thy wealth, thy worldly honour and the pompe of the world, but haſt diſpiſed them all, haſte cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them as dunge, that thou mightſt gayne Chriſt, but haſte ſolde all and haſte geuen it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, &amp; haſt followed the worde of God? Which of you, (thinkeſt thou) ſhall he are ſuch a voice of the Angel? Yea Abraham heard this voice againe the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d time and it was ſaid vnto him, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt not ſpared thy beloued ſonne for my ſake. &amp;c</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Abraham (ſaith the texte) looking back, ſaw with his eyes, and beholde. A ramme was holden by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ornes in the buſſhes of Sabet.</hi> I
<pb facs="tcp:26375:39"/>
ſuppoſe, that we haue ſaied here tofore, that Iſaac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bare the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge, this ramm ſemeth to beare the figure of Chriſte alſo. But how theſe two agree vnto Chriſt, bothe Iſaac whiche was not ſlaine, and the ramm which was, it is expediente to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Chriſte is the woorde of God, but this worde was made fleſh. There is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſt one thing which is from aboue, and an other which is taken of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of man and the woombe of the virgine. Chriſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffered his paſſion, but yet in his fleſh: he ſuffered death, but yet in his fleſh: whereof this ramme was a figure, according to the ſaing<note place="margin">Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 1.</note> of Iohn, Behold the Lambe of God, behold him whiche taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde.
<pb facs="tcp:26375:39"/>
But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde whiche is Chriſte accordinge to the Spirite, did continew in incorruption, whoſe Image this Iſaac was. So hee is the ſacrifice and highe prieſte after the ſpirite. For he that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice to his father accordinge to the fleſh, the ſelfe ſame is offered vpon the aulter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe. and lykewiſe as it is ſaid of him, Beholde the Lambe of God, Behold him who taketh away the ſinnes of the world: ſo is it alſo ſaied of him, Thou art a prieſt for euer after the order of Melchiſedech. Therfore this ramme is holden by the hornes in the buſhes of Saber.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he toke (ſaieth the text) the ram, and offered him a burnt offeringe for Iſaac his ſonne. And Abraham called the name of that place, the lord ſayth.</hi> Here is a broade way of ſpiritu
<pb facs="tcp:26375:40"/>
all vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, laied open for all them that ar ſkilful to hear theſe thinges. For all that bee here done, do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ende to ſom ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall viſion, bicauſe it is ſayed: The Lord ſeeth. This viſion of the Lord is in ſpirit, that thou alſo mayſt behold theſe thinges which are written in ſpirite: &amp; as in the Lorde there is nothing corporall or groſſe, ſo alſo that thou in all theſe thinges ſauour nothinge corporally or groſly, but that thou inwardly in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite beget to thy ſelfe a childe which may be called Iſaac, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalte obtaine the frute of the ſpirite, ioy and peace. This childe at the length thus thou may conceaue: if, (as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Sara, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was not with her, after the manner of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo ſhe bare Iſaac) all womanly
<pb facs="tcp:26375:40"/>
affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo ceaſe out of thi mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſo that thou haue no worke and effemina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinges in the ſoule: but doeſt thinges manfully, and manfully girdeſt vp thy loines, and haſt thy breſte fenſed with the breſt plate of righteouſnes, and thy ſelf armed with the hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>met of health, and the ſwerde of the ſpirit. Yt therefore ſuch wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners ceaſe in thy life, thou begetteſt a ſon, that is ioye and peace, of thy wife vertu and wiſedom. Thou begetteſt ioye, if thou ſuppoſe it all ioy, when thou ſhalt fall into diuers temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tations, &amp; canſt offer that ioye a ſacrifice to god. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou<note place="margin">Iacob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> doeſte come cherefully to God, he rendereth to thee that again which thou haſte offered, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto the: Againe ye ſhal ſee me, and your heart ſhalbe glad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26375:41"/>
and no men ſhall take your ioye from you: So then ſhalte thou receaue thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges increaſed, which thou ſhalte offer to God. Such a thinge is ſette furthe in<note place="margin">Luc. 19.</note> the goſpel although by an other figure, as where it is ſaied, that one receaued a pound for to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy, and get gaines for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good man of the houſe: And if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bring fiue increaſed into ten, they are geuen to thee thy ſelfe for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, they are graunted thee. Herken what he ſayethe: Take from this man his pounde, and geue it to him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pounde. Thus though wee ſeeme to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupye for oure Lord, yet the gai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of this matchandiſe retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to oure ſelues: though wee ſeme to offer ſacrifice to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, yet thoſe thinges which wee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer are reſtored to vs agayne.
<pb facs="tcp:26375:41"/>
For God hath not neede of anye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing, but he wold haue vs riche he wiſheth by all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes oure wealth.</p>
                  <p>Thys manner of doctrine is ſet furth vnto vs in thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whiche happened to Iob:<note place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> who beynge ryche, loſt all for Gods ſake. But becauſe hee endured well the fyghte of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicnce, becauſe he was of a ſtout courage in all thinges hee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaying: The Lorde gaue, &amp; the Lorde hath taken away: as it pleaſed the Lord, ſo is it come to paſſe, the Lords name be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed: beholde at the e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de what is written of him: He receaued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (ſaith the texte) twiſe as much as he loſte. Thou percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what it is to looſe any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges for the Lorde: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue for thy ſelfe duble: Yea
<pb facs="tcp:26375:42"/>
the goſpel doth promiſe ſom yet more; that is, it promiſeth an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred fold to the againe: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that alſo eternall lyfe, in Chriſte Ieſu oure Lorde, to whome bee glorye and empire for euer and euer.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:26375:42"/>
            <head>A prayer for mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>TERNAL GOD</hi> and moſte mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable loue towardes man (after thou haddeſte crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all thinges for his vſe and comforte) woledeſte alſo for his more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ordeine, an hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per for him of like ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and nature vnto him ſelfe, thereby knittinge the one to the other in felloſhip inſeparable. Which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of holy wedlocke thus made by the gracious contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placion, which thou hadſt to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in paradiſe, to haue it eſtemed more honorable, thou didſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate thy only begotten ſon to bee borne therin, of a moſte pure virgin. Who alſo of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable grace to the further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacion
<pb facs="tcp:26375:43"/>
of the ſaid inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vouchſaued to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally therat with his bleſſed mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther &amp; holy Apoſties, in Cane a city of Galily, &amp; there wrought his firſt &amp; notable miracle, of tourni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vnſauery water i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wine, in miſticall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame ſtate. Furdermore haſt by the mouth of thy elect veſſel Saint Paule declared the ſtate thereof to be the greate miſterye and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of that maruailous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable vniti that is betwixt Chriſt &amp; his Spouſe the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che: And for as muche as thou haſt comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uded by the ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that the huſbande ſhoulde ſo loue his wife as Chriſte lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his congregation, And that the wiſe ſhoulde ſo reuerence her huſbande, as the Church is
<pb facs="tcp:26375:43"/>
reuerently ſubiect vnto Chriſte her Spouſe.</p>
            <p>We beſech the y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony once begu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence (as we doubt not thereof) may be ſtill proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſlye continued betwixte vs. So that we may be of one heart and minde, to knowe, ſo loue, to obey and ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as thou woldeſt vs twain to be one body together, to loue and ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one thother in oure mortall life. And that we maye by the aide of thy holye ſpirite perſeuer without ſtrife, diſcord and variablenes, in perpetuall amitie and godly loue. Charita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly in our vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue with oure neighbors inſtlye in oure occupations, with the ſwete of oure browes to eate oure bread, and equally with thanks
<pb facs="tcp:26375:44"/>
to receiue of thy handes what ſo euer thy fatherlye wiſdome hath decreed to ſende vnto vs: Beſechinge furderthy godnes, that as thou haſte by thy boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous liberality geuen vs frute in this our matrimonye, ſo wee maye bee aſſiſted &amp; maintained by thy fatherly benediction, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to noriſhe them vp in their bodily life, as to inſtructe them in ſoule in thy holy Religion, to glorifie thy bleſſed name in this worlde to our lyues end, that in the nexte world we may all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the ſight of thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Maieſtie, to be vnited to thy ſelf in perpetuall felicity, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dig to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſured promiſes made vnto vs through our lorde and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the and the holy ghoſte be all honor and glorye for euer.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:26375:44"/>
            <head>A prayer generally for all parſons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me grace O moſt merciful father, to haue a feruent deſyer, euer to ſuche things as be pleaſinge to the, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye to ſearche them, wiſelye to knowledg them, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectlye to fulfil them, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land and prayſe of thy holye name. Guyde thou O Lord my lyfe &amp; lyuing, and that which thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt of me to do, graunt that I may haue a knowledg, a will and power therto. And ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthe me ſo to enſue it, as may bee to the honor of thy name, to the wealth of my neighbour, and to the healthe of my ſoule. Make the way O Lorde ſure &amp; ſtreghte
<pb facs="tcp:26375:45"/>
to thee, that I fainte not from the, neyther in proſperity, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet in aduerſity: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity I geue me not vnto pride and inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy: and that in aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity I keepe my ſelfe in hope &amp; patience: So that in aduerſitie I be not borne downe to lowe, nor yet in proſperitye I be lyft vp to hie. Suffer me not to ioye of any thinge but of that whiche may further me vnto the, and to morne of nothinge but of that whiche mighte drawe mee from the: ſo that all heauenlye thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may be loueſom to me, and all tranſitorye thinges lothſom, all fleſhly thinges yrkſom, and all greeuous thinges lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. Let all ioy be tedious to mee that is not in the, Let all paine be pleaſaunte that is for the, Let me not delite to pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:45"/>
anye creature againſte the, nor yet aferde to diſpleaſe any crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture for the. Geue me grace oft to liſte vppe my heart vnto the, and to leade my lyf ſtreight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the. Make me ſone to ryſe againe whan I fall away from the, and trulye to acknowledge &amp; confeſſe my ſinnes vnto the. Strength my faith to aſke par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don onely at the, and for Chriſts ſake mercifully to obtaine it of the. Make me O father to dred the without deſperation, and to loue the without preſumption. Make me faithfull without do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes, chaſt without fylthines, liberall without waſtefulnes, ſparinge withoute carefulnes, mery without wantonnes, ſober without ſowernes, conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with out ſtubbornes, traitable with out childiſhnes, quiet without
<pb facs="tcp:26375:46"/>
quareling, meeke without mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muringe, pacient withoute ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, obediente withoute grut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge, prudente in ſimplicitye, &amp; ſimple in prudence, cherefull in charitye, and ſeruiſable in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Geue me grace to teache my neighbour without preſump<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, to reforme him without his confuſion, to edifye him in lyfe without offenſion. Geue me a watchinge heart O Lord, that no curious thoughte diſturbe it, make it ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, that no vnworthy affection peruert it, make it con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtante, that no violente aſſaulte ſubdue it. Graunt me O father vnderſtandinge to knowe the, diligence to ſeeke the, wiſedom to fynde the, perſeueraunce to keepe the, and hope in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion to embrace thee. Let mee here be excerciſed with thy croſſe
<pb facs="tcp:26375:46"/>
to my humiliation, to recogne thin aſſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, therin to my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to vſe thy benifite; by grace, and at the laſte to obtaine thy fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in glory, to the laude and praiſe of thy bleſſed name: To whome with the Sonne, and the holye Ghoſte be all honoure for euer and euer.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by Reginalde Wolfe <hi>Anno. Do. M. D. LXV.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26375:47"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26375:47"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
